[♪♪♪]
We can't let them get away
with that weapon!
H'yah!
[Nya] Slick move.
Now, stand back.
[sparking]
Ugh! Are you wrecking my hair
on purpose?
Ugh!
I got this!
Wait, wait, wait, Jay!
I'm standing in--
N-n-n-no!
[panting]
What kind of Master of Lightning
forgets
water conducts electricity?
Maybe the kind
who suffer from amnesia.
Ugh, hate to say it, but...
that actually gave me
an idea.
Even though all of our powers
are on the fritz,
maybe if we...
combine all three together?
H'yah!
[powers surging]
[♪♪♪]
Ha!
I'm a genius.
[timer beeping]
[blasting]
What was that?
What'd they do?
An electro-magnetic pulse.
Every vehicle here is fried.
[Nya] They really
don't want us following.
[Kai] Well,
they got their wish.
Crossing the Land of Madness
on foot takes forever.
I speak from experience.
The Samurai X Mech.
The D.B. Express.
The Earth Driller!
Nya, you're like the greatest
engineer and inventor
basically ever.
Those memories are coming back?
I can't remember everything,
but everything
I remember about you
is amazing.
But all you remember about me
is my bad ideas?
What else is there?
Fried circuits or not,
I bet you can take
all these parts
and make us one working...
something?
Let's give it a shot!
[in Umbrasylvan accent]
Umbrasylvis is on lockdown
until the devious perpetrator
who released the monster
on this humble burg
can be identified, judged,
and, most importantly,
punished by a life sentence
in the restraints
of excruciation!
[townsfolk jeering]
Uh...
why is everyone shaking sticks?
"Shaking"?
They wag
Ancient Wagging Sticks,
the traditional way
of expressing oneself
in Umbrasylvan court.
Everyone knows that!
Now, there's a criminal
among us,
and their evil must be purged!
[blowing fanfare]
[shouting angrily]
As Grand Inquisitor,
I hereby declare
the inquisition begins!
♪ Lost in the unknown ♪
♪ So much to see ♪
♪ Jump up, kick back
whip around and spin ♪
♪ Together we will rise ♪
♪ Whip around and spin ♪
♪ For what's right ♪♪
True or false.
You are an outsider
to Umbrasylvis,
and thus of suspicious
character and motive.
Uh, false.
So you aren't an outsider?
No... I mean, yes.
We're not from here, but--
Were you lying then
or lying now?
Neither!
[jeering]
Don't you think a fountain
is a suspicious way
to enter a city?
Unless you're water.
Are you water?
What? No!
We didn't come through
your fountain by choice.
So you were sent here
under orders!
That's not what I said!
It seems there's a lot
you're not saying.
[townsfolk jeering]
Would you say you're known
for how much
you like to fight, Wyldfyre?
Of course!
You wanna go right now?
And would your associates
describe you
as "thriving on chaos"?
Duh.
The kind of chaos
that might result from,
oh, I don't know,
releasing
a dangerous monster?
Can I wear your tall hat?
"Hat"?
Hat?!
Let the record show
that the witness disrespected
the Mantle of Righteousness!
[shouting angrily]
I think it's obvious here
who the culprit is.
She was with the dragon, sir.
The outsider known as Wyldfyre
was in my windmill
with the dragon, Riyu,
all night.
Wouldn't leave his side.
She couldn't possibly
have let that monster out.
Interesting,
and were her companions
also with the dragon?
Almost all night.
"Almost"?
But you can't account
for their whereabouts
at every moment?
Very interesting.
The Explorers Club
adheres to strict regulations.
Members are required
to log their comings and goings
on the ship
in this book.
Now, as you can see,
each member of the expedition
is accounted for last night.
Those entries could've been
written whenever.
That's easily faked.
Nonsense!
These records are immaculate.
No one with margins that clean
would falsify records!
And do the names
of the other outsiders,
these "nin-jah,"
appear anywhere in the logbook?
No.
Can you vouch
for any of the "nin-jah" at all?
No.
I cannot.
Isn't it true
that you were on the airship
the night in question?
I already told you,
we went there
to get a cure for Riyu.
And yet your names
do not appear
on the aforementioned logbook.
We didn't even know
about that stupid book.
[townsfolk gasping]
So you snuck onto a ship,
violated its regulations,
and released the monster
on an innocent population!
That's not what happened!
We shall see.
The Court must gather
additional facts
based on today's testimony.
In the meantime,
bring forth the shame boards!
"Warning: Dangerous Suspect."
Are these really necessary?
[Grand Inquisitor]
Very much so.
A Thread of Truth
is woven through each cord.
I will know if the signs
are removed.
Such an act would result
in an immediate guilty verdict!
This inquisition is in recess!
I think I'd make
a pretty good Inquisitor
since I'm always right,
and I look good in hats.
I can't believe my dad
wouldn't vouch for us.
You saw someone with a mask
on that airship last night.
Someone who probably
didn't sign that book either.
Yeah...
We gotta find that weirdo,
or we'll be declared guilty
for sure.
Well, the Inquisitor
isn't the only one
who knows how to inquire.
Any clues
have to be on the airship.
Let's go.
I don't know how to help them.
[wheezing]
[gasping]
It's a seedling!
-[Acona chittering]
-Huh?
[chittering]
I think they want us
to plant it.
[Arc Dragon] I've never
seen the wood reach this point.
I don't know
how much longer it--
or I--
can hold on,
and if the Whispering Wood
falls,
the Merged Lands
will eventually fall too.
[thudding heavily]
[Arc Dragon] You are...
comforting me?
Though you are only
a simulation of life,
your emotions seem almost real.
I may sometimes struggle
to communicate my feelings,
but I feel them
as deeply as anyone else.
[chittering]
[Arc Dragon] Thank you for
being with me at the very end.
Maybe this isn't the end.
Believe in Lloyd.
There have been many times
when he's faced dire situations
and come out stronger.
[Arc Dragon]
That is false hope.
At his age,
Lloyd is too deeply rooted
in his path
to cut himself free and live.
[chittering excitedly]
The Whispering Wood
and its guardian,
the Green Ninja,
may be more resilient
than even you realize.
[wind blowing]
So, exactly how long
would I have kept that haircut?
Whatever, dork.
You wanna talk hair?
How old was I
when I forgot what a comb was?
No wonder I still don't
have a girlfriend.
Hey!
I'm busy taking care
of a whole monastery, and--
Whatever.
Look, I'm here to prepare you
for the rest of the ritual.
You?
[grunting]
You ready, punk?
Sometimes I think "exploring"
is just code for stealing.
You really think
we're going to find a clue
in one of these crates?
It'd help identify our suspect
if we had a motive.
They've gotta be
hiding something somewhere.
Careful!
Show-off.
Wha...!
Oh!
A-ha!
A scale!
We have our villain!
Who?
There's only one Explorer
who could have left this!
My father!
You think your dad did it?
You defended him
when I suggested he maybe
wasn't such a great dad.
Our relationship is...
complicated,
but you heard him
at the inquisition.
He couldn't put his neck
on the line for his own son.
Why? He's guilty.
But the Expedition
has been using this ship
for a while.
Your dad could've
shed this scale
at any point
during their travels.
Yeah.
The Inquisitor
is gonna need more
to prove his guilt.
Let's keep searching.
After we heard that scream,
I came here,
and found my dad wearing a mask,
back there in the dark.
We don't know it was your dad.
I do. Come on.
[grunting] Oh--
[chuckling awkwardly]
Ooh, sorry.
[laughing]
[grunting]
Yeah.
No door. No air vent.
No way out.
Why would he free a monster
only to back himself
into a corner?
Huh...
this material looks newer
than the rest of the corridor.
[clicking]
[gasping]
[hatch creaking open]
Whoa!
Blast from the past.
It's Imperium tech,
the model that was used
in the Advanced Systems Lab.
Where would my dad get that?
Maybe it's stolen?
[scoffing]
He's good at that.
"Exploring."
It's analyzing
the monster's energy signature
and searching for resonance
somewhere in Umbrasylvis.
But you don't have to
break a monster loose
to study it.
Maybe they needed readings
as it moved around,
to triangulate
synchronous energy sources.
Oh, yes, the synchronous...
S-synchronous.
It's still processing
the readings,
trying to find the location
of the resonant item,
but I might be able
to give it a boost if I--
There! Found the location.
We don't know
what he was searching for,
but we do know where it is.
You're putting it back?
The only way
to prove their identity
is to give them
exactly what they want...
And be there to ambush them
when they try to get it.
Ha!
My dad won't see us coming!
-[grunting]
-Whoa!
Too slow!
[laughing obnoxiously]
I forgot what a brat
I could be sometimes.
You coming or not?
Whoa! [grunting]
[Tween Lloyd] What did I say?
I'm a path you didn't take,
so take a different path.
H'yah!
What did you think
of your vision?
I saw a network of roots.
The trees were all...
connected somehow?
And when one needed help,
the others gave it nutrients.
-[nearby] And...
-[gasping]
what does that tell you
about the power
of the Green Ninja?
Or do you need to get stuck
under the dirt again?
Aah!
[screaming]
Think.
How did we get our powers?
The Golden Weapons...
and the other Ninja.
They surrounded me.
I could feel their energy,
but what does that
have to do with--?
Aah!
[screaming]
[grunting]
Power comes from within,
but... not all of it.
Some of our power comes from...
those around us?
Our friends,
our family,
our community?
[Tween Lloyd] Bingo.
Each tree is connected.
Trees are life.
You are the Master of Life.
The Elemental Master of Life
is the master of the connection
between and through all things.
Just as you gained your powers
through others'
connection to you,
your true potential
can only manifest
when you connect
to those around you.
[♪♪♪]
It's beautiful, in a sad way.
The Tree of Burdens.
I overheard a local
talking about it.
Each ribbon represents a worry.
You tie a ribbon to the tree
hoping its branches
will help bear the weight
of your problem.
Guess that's why
it's so twisted and bent.
Wish I had a ribbon for my dad.
Being perfect
was the only way
I could get his attention,
but it was never enough.
I was never enough.
You're more than enough.
Sometimes too much.
[footsteps approaching]
[door opening]
[Frak] That could be Dad.
Quick, hide!
[whispering]
Come on, let's grab him.
Let's see what he wants
with the tree first.
It may be a clue to fighting
the Elemental Monsters.
[beeping]
What could that thing be?
That's enough.
[Sora] Frak, wait!
Stop!
I know it's you, Dad!
[weapon charging]
[grunting]
Leave my son alone!
[gasping] Dad?
How?
Ha!
Johnny Courageous?
You betrayed
the Explorer's Club?
Jolly bad form, old boy!
[gasping] You are Imperian!
Civil servant class?
What did you take
from the Tree?
Tell her
I don't speak to traitors.
Traitor?
I helped liberate Imperium!
You helped it fall!
All Hail The Good Empress!
"The Good Empress"? What?
[Frak] At least this Empress
won't get whatever this is--
[power surging]
[rumbling]
[gasping]
[weapon charging]
Something's happening!
I can't control this!
[Reggie]
It's going to be okay, son.
[Frak gasps]
[rumbling]
You have to let it go.
[straining]
[rumbling stops]
Yes, this handkerchief
was enchanted
by the Pontifex Magicus
of Mysterium.
Not my first time
handling a cursed relic.
We're, uh, gonna need that.
Hopefully it will help
clear our name
with the Inquisitor.
Oh, right, right.
Uh, sorry.
I'm not all that familiar
with handing over
rare artifacts.
Thanks, Dad.
I overheard you.
You thought the villain...
was me?
I did.
'Cause it was easy to believe.
Egads!
I take offense.
You didn't even try
to defend me in that court.
But why would you have?
You were never there for me
when I needed you.
Gone for every
important moment in my life,
chasing some discovery
that would be your legacy?
Guess you never thought
I could be your legacy.
[sighing]
Frak, I just wanted you
to have a father
you could be proud of.
You don't know
what it used to be like
for Serpentine in Ninjago.
"Never trust a snake,"
they used to say.
I had to work twice as hard
for twice as long
to get any recognition.
Yeah, well,
you didn't even work
half as hard
at being a good dad.
Why'd the Temple
show you to me?
I'd just accepted the incident
with Tomorrow's Tea
as another part of my destiny.
The Ritual of Unrooting
requires you to understand
your connections to others,
even to other yous.
Who you were.
Who you could have been.
Who you might become.
Remember that
for this next part.
Uh, next part?
This wasn't the test?
[chuckling]
Are you serious?
All this was just to give you
a fighting chance in there.
[ground cracking]
Meditate on your past
and prepare for the future.
Through that archway
is your greatest foe.
Who?
An enemy you've faced
many times.
One you've temporarily bested,
but never truly defeated.
Huh...
That doesn't really
narrow it down.
[Tween Lloyd] Only by
defeating this enemy
will you be able
to fully connect
to the pathways
of the Whispering Wood
and embrace your power
as the Legendary Green Ninja.
Hey, wait.
I know you're just
a manifestation,
but I need to know...
are you happy?
You tell me.
[Lloyd sighs]
[townsfolk murmuring]
The inquisition
is back in session!
[clearing his throat]
Well, if the accused
can't even bother to show up,
that seems like proof enough.
I hereby pronounce them guil--
[Sora] Not so fast!
Here's your culprit.
He pulled this
out of the Tree of Burdens.
[gasping]
Only a true villain
would defile the sacred tree.
I declare this miscreant guilty!
[banging staff]
These two are cleared
of all suspicion!
Lockdown lifted!
Inquisition complete!
[blowing fanfare]
-[crowd cheering]
-Whoa.
[cheering]
[Grand Inquisitor]
The only thing left to do now
is deliver this
to the Good Empress...
[cheers turn to confusion]
What?!
[Umbrasylvan accent gone]
Endless months of deep cover
in this miserable backwater
is finally over!
You ignorant yokels,
I'm part of the future,
not the past!
All Hail The Good Empress.
[device beeping]
[coughing]
[gasping] Where did he--?
[engines whirring overhead]
He's taking the airship!
If Empress Beatrix
is really back,
we're all in more danger
than we ever imagined!
[♪♪♪]